<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A book of the continuation of forreign passages That is, of the peace made between this Common-wealth, &amp; that of the united Provinces of the Netherlands, with all the articles of that peace. Apr. 5. 1654. And the articles of peace, friendship and entercourse agreed between England and Sweden, in a treaty at Usall. May 9. 1654. As also the substance of the articles of the treaty of peace betwixt England and France. Given at White Hall the 20 of Novemb: 1655. From Generall Blakes fleet, the Turks in Argier do consent to deliver up all the English slaves, and desire a firme peace for ever: and in Tunnis road we battered their castle of Porta-ferina, and set on fire their fleet in the harbour. Apr. 9. 1655. Moreover, an attempt on the island of Jamaica, and taking the town of St. Jago de la viga, beating the enemy from their forts and ordnance, being a body of 3000 men, and so took possession of the island, May 10 1655. With a full description thereof. With a true narrative of the late successe ... against the King of Spains West India </title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28784</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832792</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832792</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37266</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28784)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37266)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2185:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A book of the continuation of forreign passages That is, of the peace made between this Common-wealth, &amp; that of the united Provinces of the Netherlands, with all the articles of that peace. Apr. 5. 1654. And the articles of peace, friendship and entercourse agreed between England and Sweden, in a treaty at Usall. May 9. 1654. As also the substance of the articles of the treaty of peace betwixt England and France. Given at White Hall the 20 of Novemb: 1655. From Generall Blakes fleet, the Turks in Argier do consent to deliver up all the English slaves, and desire a firme peace for ever: and in Tunnis road we battered their castle of Porta-ferina, and set on fire their fleet in the harbour. Apr. 9. 1655. Moreover, an attempt on the island of Jamaica, and taking the town of St. Jago de la viga, beating the enemy from their forts and ordnance, being a body of 3000 men, and so took possession of the island, May 10 1655. With a full description thereof. With a true narrative of the late successe ... against the King of Spains West India </title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60+ : ill., port., map (metalcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M.S. for Thomas Jenner at the south entrance of the Royall Exhange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through; lacks all after p. 60.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Sweden --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Turkey --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jamaica --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37266:1"/>
            <p>A BOOK OF THE Continuation <hi>of</hi> Forreign Paſſages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That is,</hi> Of the Peace made between this Common-wealth, &amp; that of the united Provinces of the Netherlands, with all the Articles of that Peace. <hi>Apr.</hi> 5. 1654.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the</hi> Articles of Peace, Friendſhip and Entercourſe agreed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> in a Treaty at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſall. May</hi> 9. 1654.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo</hi> The ſubſtance of the Articles of the Treaty of Peace betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> Given at White Hall the 20 of <hi>Novemb:</hi> 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From Generall</hi> Blakes <hi>Fleet,</hi> The Turks in <hi>Argier</hi> do conſent to deliver up all the Engliſh ſlaves, and deſire a firme Peace for ever: And in <hi>Tunnis</hi> Road we battered their Caſtle of <hi>Porta-ferina,</hi> and ſet on fire their fleet in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. <hi>Apr.</hi> 9. 1655.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>MOREOVER, An attempt on the Iſland of</hi> Jamaica, <hi>and taking the Town of St.</hi> Jago de la viga, <hi>beating the Enemy from their Forts and Ordnance, being a body of</hi> 3000 <hi>men, and ſo took poſſeſſion of the Iſland,</hi> May 10 1655. <hi>With a full Deſcription thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a true Narrative of the late Succeſſe which it hath pleaſed God to give to ſome part of the Fleet of this Common-wealth, the Speaker, the Bridg-water, the Plimouth Frigots, againſt the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Weſt India Fleet: the value of what is taken and poseſſed by the calculation of the Spaniards about nine millions of pieces of eight, and 350 priſoners, and all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loſſe of one veſſell of the Engliſh, 1656.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He hath ſhewed his people the power of his works, that he may give them the heritage of the Heathen,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 111.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Jenner</hi> at the South entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:37266:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37266:2"/>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two armies facing each other, with figures on horses bearing flags between them; in foreground, three figures on horses facing the viewer</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A <hi>PROCLAMATION</hi> of the Peace made between this Common-wealth, and that of the United Provinces of the Netherlands.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS Highneſſe the Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> conſidering how neceſſary it is not onely to preſerve Peace and Quiet at home, but as far as in him lies, to live in Amity and Friendſhip with his Neighbours, hath by the bleſſing of God, with the advice of his Councell made and concluded a Peace, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and Confederation to continue for ever, between this Common-wealth of the one part, and that of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces of the Low-Countries of the other part; their Lands, Countries, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Territories, Places and People, by Sea, Land, Freſh waters, and elſewhere; by the which Peace it is agreed, That all Enmity, Hostility, Diſcord and War between the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37266:3"/>ſaid Common-wealths, their People and Subjects ſhall ceaſe, and all injuries and wrongs whatſoever done ſince the <hi>18</hi> of <hi>May, 1652.</hi> ſhall ceaſe and be forgotten, except ſuch depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations as ſhall be committed by either ſide in theſe Seas after <hi>12</hi> days, from the date of theſe preſents, and in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places on this ſide the Cape of St. <hi>Vincent,</hi> after ſix weeks; and from thence, within the <hi>Mediteranean</hi> Sea, and to the <hi>Aequinoctial Line,</hi> after ten weeks; and beyond the <hi>Aequinoctiall Line,</hi> after the ſpace of <hi>8</hi> Months, or immediately after ſufficient notice of the ſaid Peace given in thoſe places. And that the people and Inhabitants of each party reſpectively, of what condition or quality ſoever they be, ſhall treat each other with love and friendſhip, and may freely and ſecurely come into, and paſſe through each others Countries, Towns, Villages and Precincts, and there ſtay and abide, and from thence depart again at their pleaſure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hinderance and moleſtation, and likewiſe trade and have eommerce, and generally doe uſe, and exerciſe all other things (obſerving the Laws and Cuſtomes of each place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively) as freely, fully and ſecurely as they might have done in time of Peace: Whereof all perſons whatſoever in theſe Nations of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> are to take notice, and conforme themſelves accordingly. </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at White Hall</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this 26 of</hi> April, <hi>1654.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>O. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles of Peace, <hi>abreviated,</hi> April <hi>5. 1654.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. IT is agreed, concluded, and accorded, that from this day forward there ſhall be a true, firm and inviolable Peace, betwixt the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> and the States Generall of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the reſpective Lands, Countries, and Cities, without diſtinction of places, under their obedience.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37266:3"/>
            <p n="2">II. That from henceforth all enmity, hoſtility, diſcord and War betwixt the ſaid two Common-wealths, their People and Subjects, ſhall ceaſe, by Sea, Land, and freſh-waters.</p>
            <p n="3">III. All offences, injuries, charges, and damages, which either party hath ſuſtained by the other, ſince the 18 (<hi>alias</hi> 28) of <hi>May,</hi> 1652. ſhall be taken away and forgotten. And all actions for the ſame ſhall be held and reputed voyd and null.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. All Priſoners of both ſides, of what condition, or in whatſoever places they be, ſhall be ſet at liberty.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The two Common-wealths ſhall remain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate friends, joyned, and allied together for the defence and preſervation of the Liberties and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of each againſt all whomſoever, or be declared Enemies to the Freedome and Liberty of the people living under either of the ſaid Governments.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Neither of the Common-wealths ſhall make, doe, act, treat of, or attempt any thing againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or the people of either, in any place either at Land or Sea, upon any occaſion whatſoever. Nor that either of them, or the people of either, give, yield, or afford any aide, counſel, favour, or aſſent that any thing ſhall be done, treated of, or attempted by any other whomſoever, to the injury and wrong of the other, but ſhall expreſly contradict, gainſay, oppoſe, and really hinder all whomſoever, that act, do, treat of, or attempt any thing againſt either of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. Neither of the Commonwealths, or the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple abiding, inhabiting, or dwelling within either of them reſpectively, ſhall yield, give, or afford any aid counſel or favour to the Enemies or Rebels of either, but ſhall expreſly, really, and with effect hinder either
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37266:4"/>of them from giving any aide or aſſiſtance, by Men Shipping, Arms, Ammunition, Money, Victualls, or otherwiſe by Sea or Land, and all ſuch Ships or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, that ſhall be made uſe of, contrary to the intent of this Article, ſhall be forfeited to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Commonwealths, and the perſons imployed therein, declared Enemies to both Commonwealths, and ſuffer the penalties of Treaſon where the offence was committed. And to the end there may be a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication made of what Goods ſhall be deemed prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, or contraband, Commiſſioners may in conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time be appointed to determine herein. Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that this extend not to the impeachment of any thing contained in the preſent Article.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The two Common-wealths ſhall truly and ſincerely aſſiſt each other as need ſhall require, againſt the Rebels of either, at Sea and Land, at the coſts and expences of the party requiring the ſame, upon ſuch conditions as the two States ſhall agree.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. That neither of the Common-wealths ſhall receive any perſon or perſons, that are Enemies to the other, nor afford any aid, counſel, lodging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but ſhall expreſly and effectually, oppoſe and hinder the ſame.</p>
            <p n="10">X. That if either Common-wealth ſhall by their publick Letters ſignifie to the other, any perſons to be, and have been their Enemies, that they reſide, be hid, or ſhelter themſelves in their Juriſdictions, that Common-wealth receiving ſuch Letters, ſhall within 28 dayer charge ſuch Enemy to depart their Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, and if they ſhall not depart within 15 days, to be puniſhed with death, and loſſe of lands &amp; goods.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. No Rebel of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall by any be received into any place of the United
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37266:4"/>Provinces: And if any perſon under their power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the contrary, ſuch perſon ſhall forfeit and looſe their Caſtles, Towns, which they ſhall at ſuch time have or pretend to have. And no declared Enemy of the United Provinces ſhall be received into any places holden or poſſeſſed in <hi>England,</hi> but they ſhall hinder the ſame, and in caſe of contempt, forfeit the ſame.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. Both Common wealths ſhall treat on both ſides with all love and friendſhip, and come by water or land to each Havens, with freedome, and continue there as long as they pleaſe, and trade in any goods, paying Cuſtomes, ſaving always all and ſingular the Lawes and Ordinances of either Common-wealth reſpectively.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. The Ships and Veſſels of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, meeting any the Ships of War of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in the Brittiſh Seas, ſhall ſtrike their Flag and lower their Top-ſaile.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. Neither of the ſaid Common-wealths ſhall receive into any of their Havens, or give affiſtance or relief unto any Pirates or Sea-Rovers, but ſhall cauſe them to be apprehended, all ſhips taken, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the right owners, or made good to them.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. That if either Common-wealth, ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after make any Treaty with any other Nation, the one ſhall give notice to, and comprehend the other, if they deſire it.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. If during the Amity, any thing ſhall be acted againſt this Treaty, it ſhall not be hereby inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or broken off, onely thoſe particular perſons who have offended, ſhall be puniſhed, and ſatisfaction made to all perſons concerned, after 12 month de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding thereof, in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> within the Straights of <hi>Gilbralter,</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> upon the Coaſts of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37266:5"/>
               <hi>Africk,</hi> or on this ſide the Cape of Good Hope, and beyond the ſaid Cape within 18 months, and in caſe the offenders ſhall not ſubmit themſelves to Juſtice, they ſhall be declared Enemies to both Common-wealths, their Eſtates confiſcate, and perſons liable to ſuch further puniſhments, as their offence ſhall deſerve.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. The people of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> may freely, unmoleſted, and ſecurely travell in and through the Countries of the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Europe,</hi> in them, or beyond them, to follow their Traffick in all places there; as alſo their Factors or Servants, armed or unarmed; but if armed, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 40 men in company. And the people the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> may injoy the ſame liberty in the Common-wealth of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> they conforming to the Laws thereof.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. If the Merchant Ships of one or the other ſide, ſhall through Tempeſt, Pirats, or any other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, be driven into the Ports of either, it ſhall be free for them to depart without payment of any Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, or other duties; provided they break not bulk, or expoſe any thing to ſale.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. The Merchants, Maſters, Pilots, or Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, of either Common-wealth, their Ships or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes ſhall not be ſeized or arreſted in the Lands, or Rivers of the other, for any warlike or other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, except upon inevitable neceſſity, and juſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the ſame; provided that hereby ſhall not be excluded the Arreſts and Seizures in the ordinary way of Law of each Common-wealth.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. The Merchants on both ſides, and the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, may by Sea and Land, carry all ſorts of Arms for defence and offence; but being come to their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37266:5"/>Inns, ſhall lay down their Arms, and ſo leave them till they return on board again.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. The Men of War of either Commonwealth, meeting or overtaking any Merchants Ship belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the other, or holding both one courſe, ſhall take them under their protection, and defend them againſt all attempts.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. If a Ship of either Common-wealth, or a Newrer, ſhall be taken in the Havens of either by any third party; they, in or from whoſe Haven the ſaid Ships ſhall be taken, ſhall endeavor the re-taking of the ſaid Ship, at the charge of the proprietors.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. That Searchers on both parts, ſhall regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late themſelves according to the Laws of each Com: and not levy or take more they are allowed.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. In caſe wrong be done, againſt any the Articles of this Treaty, no Letters of Reprizall, Mark or Countermark ſhall be granted, till firſt Juſtice be ſought, and in caſe Juſtice be refuſed or delayed, and no ſatisfaction made within 3 months, then Letters of Reprizall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be granted.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. All perſons going to Sea, having particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Commiſſions, ſhall put in ſecurity to doe no wrong to either ſide.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. Free acceſſe ſhall be granted to each others Ports, with Merchants Ships, and Men of war, ſo they exceed not the number of 8 Ships of War, nor ſtay longer then for the reparation of their Ships; and if any greater number, then it is not lawfull to make entrance without firſt obtaining leave from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, and make no longer ſtay then he ſhall permit, and during their ſtay ſhall commit no hoſtile act, or do any thing to the prejudice of the ſaid Ports.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. The Lords of the United Provinces ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37266:6"/>take care that Juſtice be done on the Authors of the Murther of the Engliſh in <hi>Amboyna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. Whereas certain Engliſh Ships and Goods have been ſeized and detained within the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> ſince <hi>May</hi> 18. 1652. the States Generall have oblidged themſelves, That reſtitution ſhall be made of all the Engliſh Ships and Goods detained yet in <hi>ſpecie;</hi> together with the true and juſt price of ſuch as are ſold, imbezled, or otherwiſe diſpoſed of, within 14 days after the arrival of the Merchants for the receiving of them. And alſo that Damages be given for the loſſes ſuſtained by the Engliſh, by reaſon of the ſaid detention, according to what ſhall be arbitrated by <hi>Edw: Winſlow, James Ruſſel, John Beex, Wil: Vander Cruyſſen,</hi> on the part of the Lord Protector, and the States Generall, to examine the demands of the Merchants; and to meet at <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> Hall, <hi>London,</hi> June 27. and make Oath before the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty, that they will proceed without reſpect to any particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt whatſoever. And the 1 of <hi>Aug:</hi> next, unleſſe they agree upon Sentence ſooner, be ſhut up in a Chamber by themſelves without fire, candle, meat, drink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till ſuch time as they come to an agreement, and the award ſhall be Obligatory to both parties. And the States Generall do firmly Oblige themſelves to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame, to pay ſuch ſum of money here at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> as the ſaid Arbitrators ſhall a judge to be paid for the uſe of the ſaid Owners, as the L: Protector ſhall nominate within 25 dayes after the adjudication made, and the States Gen: ſhall pay at <hi>London</hi> the ſum of 5000 <hi>l. ſter.</hi> towards the Charges of the Merchants, Maſters, or their Aſſigns, for their Journy to <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the ſum of 20000 Rix Dollars, to ſuch perſons as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37266:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Highneſſe ſhall appoint, within 6 days after their arrivall there. Which ſaid ſums ſhall be accounted in part of payment of ſuch ſum, as ſhall be ſo awarded. And that ſecurity ſhall be given by ſufficient men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in <hi>London,</hi> binding themſelves in 140000 <hi>l. ſterl.</hi> that reſtitution ſhall be made according to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: and that the 20000 Rix Dollars ſhall on their part be duely performed. And if all the Conditions be not really performed, then the ſaid ſum of 140000 <hi>l. ſterl.</hi> ſhall be paid to ſuch perſons as his Highneſſe ſhall nominate, that the Merchants loſſes may be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. The States Gen: have undertaken the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Ships and Goods, and the ſame being performed, all queſtions, ſtrifes, and wrongs between the ſaid Common-wealth and King ſhall ceaſe and be for ever forgotten, and ſhal be as a friend comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and included in this Treaty &amp; Confederation.</p>
            <p n="30">XXX. That at the time of the delivery of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Ratification, four Commiſſioners ſhall be nominated on both ſides to meet here at <hi>London, May</hi> 18. to examine and determine all the loſſes and injuries which either ſide alleges to have ſuſtained from the other ſince the year 1611. unto <hi>May</hi> 18. 1652. as well in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> as in <hi>Greenland, Muſcovy, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> or any other place. And if the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall not within 3 months come to an agreement, the differences ſhall be ſubmmitted to the judgement and arbitration of the Proteſtant Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> who by an Inſtrument for this purpoſe, ſhall be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red-to take upon them that Arbitration, and appoint like Commiſſioners impowred and inſtructed to give finall judgement thereupon within 6 months after the expiration of the 3 months; and whatſoever the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37266:7"/>major part of them ſhall award, ſhall oblige both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and be performed accordingly.</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. It is agreed, That both parties ſhall well and truly perform, and cauſe to be performed, this preſent Treaty.</p>
            <p n="32">XXXII. The States General do by theſe preſents, firmly oblige themſelves, that all and ſigular whom, ſhall at any time elect, conſtitute, or appoint, Capt. Gen. <hi>Stadtholder,</hi> Commander of their Army, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of any of their Fleets, ſhall confirm by Oath this Treaty, all the things therein contained, and ſhall promiſe to perform and keep the ſame.</p>
            <p n="33">XXXIII. Laſtly, it is agreed that the preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall within 15 days next, be confirmed and ratified in due and authentick form, by the ſaid L: Protector, and the ſaid States Gen: of the United Provinces, by their Letters, Patents under their Great Seals, and that Inſtruments of Ratification ſhall be delivered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terchangeably, within the time aforeſaid. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore that this Treaty and Conſederation ſhall immediately after delivery of the Inſtruments, be pubiſhed, according to the uſuall ſolemnity, and in the places accuſtomed; and that all Acts of Hoſtility ſhall ceaſe on both ſides from that time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles of Peace, Friendſhip and Entercourſe concluded and agreed between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Sweden.</hi> May <hi>9. 1654.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>portrait of man with mustache, short curly hair, no beard, high neck ruff, and armor (?)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p n="2">II. The ſaid Confederates their People, Subjects and Inhabitants ſhall, as opportunity is offered, take care of, and promote the welfare each of other. And ſhall advertiſe each other, upon knowledge thereof, of all imminent dangers, plots, and conſpiracies of Enemies againſt the other; and, as much as in them lies, oppoſe, and hinder the ſame. Neither ſhall the one Confederate, either by himſelf, or any elſe, treat of, act, or attempt any thing to the prejudice and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of the other, his Lands or Dominions, in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37266:8"/>whatſoever place, whether at Sea or Land; nor ſhall any way aſſiſt the Rebells or Enemies of the other, to the damage of the Confederate, nor receive, or enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine within his Dominions, any Rebell or Traytor, who ſhall attempt any thing againſt the others State, much leſſe afford them any Council, help or favour, or permit it to be done by any of his Subjects, People and Inhabitants.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The ſaid Protector and Commonwealth, and the ſaid Queen &amp; Kingdome ſhall take diligent care, That, as much as in them lies, all impediments and obſtacles be removed, which have hitherto interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the freedome of Navigation and Commerce, as well between both Nations, as with other People and Countries within the Dominions, Lands, Seas and Rivers of either. And ſhall ſincerely endeavor to aſſert maintain, defend and promote the aforeſaid Liberty of Navigation and Commerce againſt all the Diſturbers thereof, by ſuch ways and means, as either in this preſent Treaty, or hereafter ſhall be agreed upon. Neither ſhall they ſuffer, that either by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Subjects and People, or through their default, any thing be done or committed contrary hereunto.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That either of the aforeſaid Confederates their People and Subjects, may without any ſafe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, licence, generall or ſpeciall freely and ſecurely go and enter by Land or Sea, in and to the Kingdoms, Countries, Provinces, Lands, Iſlands, Cities, Villages, Towns, whether walled or unwalled, fortified, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, Havens and whatſoever Dominions of the other, and there ſtay and from thence return or paſſe through; and in the ſame places, upon juſt prices to procure, and have proviſion of Victuals, for their uſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37266:8"/>and ſuſtenance and to be uſed with all friendly Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And that either Confederate, their People and ſubjects may trade and have commerce in all places where commerce hath hitherto been exerciſed, in what Goods and Merchandiſes they pleaſe, and may freely import and export the ſame, paying the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms which are due, and conforming themſelves to the Laws and Ordinances of the ſaid Commonwealth and Kingdome, whether the ſame reſpect Trade or any other right; which preſuppoſed, the People, ſubjects and inhabitants of both Confederates, ſhall have and enjoy in each others Kingdoms, Countries, Lands and Dominions, as large and ample privileges, Relaxations, Liberties and immunities, as any other Foreiner at preſent doth, or hereafter ſhall enjoy there.</p>
            <p n="5">V. No Merchants, Captains, and Maſters of Ships, Mariners, nor any other Perſons, Ships, Goods, or Merchandize belonging to either Confederate ſhall upon any publique, or private account, by virtue of any Edict Generall or ſpeciall, within any the Lands, Havens, Sea roads, Coaſts, or Dominions of the other, for any publick ſervice, or expedition of war, or any other cauſe, much leſſe for any private uſe, be ſeized, embargued, arreſted, forced by violence, or be any way moleſted or injured, provided onely ſuch arreſts as are conformable to juſtice and equity be not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prohibited, ſo be it they are made according to the ordinary courſe of Law, and not granted upon private affection, or partiality, but are requiſite for the adminiſtration of right and juſtice.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. In caſe any of the Ships of either Confederate, whether of War or Merchants, belonging to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects &amp; People of either, be by occaſion of Tempeſts,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37266:9"/>purſuit of Pyrates and Enemies, or any other urgent neceſſity conſtrained to put into each others Havens, Roads or ſhores, they ſhall be received there with all kindneſſe and humanity, and enjoy all friendly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and be permitted to refreſh themſelves and procure at a reaſonable price, all things needfull for their ſuſtenance, reparation, or uſe. Neither ſhall they be hindred from going out of the ſaid Ports or Roads, at their pleaſure, without paying any cuſtoms or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Provided they do nothing contrary to the Laws Ordinances and Cuſtoms of the place, which the ſaid Ships ſhall enter into or abide in.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. In like manner, if any Ship or Ships whether publick or private, belonging to either Confederate, their People and Subjects, ſhall within any the Coaſts or Dominions of the other, ſtick upon the ſands, or be forced to lighten their burden, or be wrack'd, or ſuffer any damage, all friendly help and reliefe ſhall be given them upon a competent reward. And what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall be remaining of the goods thrown over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board or after ſhipwrack, or any other damage ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhall be kept in ſafe cuſtody, and reſtored to the Owner, or whom the ſaid Owner ſhall appoynt.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. In caſe the People and Subjects on either part, whether they be Merchants, Factors, or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Maſters of Ships, Mariners, or ſuch others, who travell and inhabit within the Dominions of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or thoſe who act on their behalfe before any Court of Judicature, for recovery of their Debts, or for other lawfull occaſions, ſhall ſtand in need of the Magiſtrates help, the ſame ſhall be readily, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the equity of their Cauſe, in friendly manner granted them, and Juſtice ſhall be adminiſtred to them without long and unneceſſary Delays. Neither
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37266:9"/>ſhall they be any way moleſted upon any pretence in the Diſpatch of their Affairs, in their Journeying, Bargaining, and Receiving the Price of their Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, but that all Love and Friendſhip be extended towards them. And it ſhall be free for them on both ſides, in their paſſage to and again, in each others Coaſts, Ships, Havens, and Publick Places, to wear about them Arms for their proper defence, ſo be it they give no juſt ſuſpition to the Governour or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the place, of any deſign againſt the publick or private peace. But he eſpecially who behaves and demeans himſelfe ſoberly and inoffenſively, ſhall be protected from all injury, violence &amp; moleſtation.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The ſaid Confederates, and all and ſingular their People and Subjects, may buy and export out of all the Countries, Dominions and Kingdomes of the other, all kind of Armour and Proviſion of War, and may ſafely and freely put in with their Ships, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at each others Ports, Havens and Shores, and there ſtay, and thence depart, they carrying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves peaceably, and conformably to the Laws and Cuſtomes of the reſpective places, and not diſturbing the freedome of commerce therein. In like manner the Ships of War ſhall have free acceſſe to the Ports of either, there to ſtay, and come to anchor, but not in ſuch numbers as ſhall occaſion manifeſt ſuſpition, without the leave and conſent of that Confederate firſt obtained, to whom the Port belongs, unleſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled thereto by tempeſt, force, or danger of the Sea, in which caſe they ſhall ſignifie to the Governor, or chief Magiſtrate of the Place, the cauſe of their Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall, and ſhall continue there no longer then the ſaid Governor ſhall permit. Obſerving always the Laws aforeſaid, and ſuch as ſhall hereafter be agreed upon.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:37266:10"/>
            <p n="10">X. The Subjects and Inhabitants of the Queen and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> may ſafely and freely travell in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereof, and paſſe through the ſame by Sea or Land, to any other Nations freely to traffick and have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with them in all ſorts of merchandize, and to import and export the ſame. And the People of the ſaid Commonwealth ſhall enjoy the ſame freedome in the Kingdomes, Dominions and Territories, of the Queen and Kingdome of <hi>Sweden.</hi> Provided, the Laws, Ordinances, and particular rights of each Nation, concerning Trade and Commerce be obſerved, on both ſides.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. Although in the preceeding Articles of this preſent Treaty, it be forbid to either Confederate to yield any aid or aſſiſtance to the Enemies of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet it is not to be ſo underſtood, as if either Confederate having no War with the Enemies of the other, might not ſaile to, or traffick with the ſaid Enemies, notwithſtanding the other Confederate be in actuall war with them; But it is onely provided, That till a more particular agreement be made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, no goods called goods of <hi>Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banda,</hi> a Catalogue and Specification of which ſhall be made within 4 months after the date hereof, ſhall be carried to the Enemies of each other without peril in caſe they be taken, of being adjudged lawful prize without hope of Reſtitution.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. But leſt ſuch Navigation and Entercourſe of the one Confederate, his People &amp; Subjects by Land or Sea, with other Nations, during the War of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confederate, ſhould redound to the prejudice of the other Confed: And leſt goods of Enemies, ſhould paſſe concealed under the name of Friends; for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37266:10"/>removall of all ſuſpition and prevention of fraud herein, it is agreed, That all Ships, Waggons, Wares and men, belonging to either Confederate, ſhall in their paſſage, have Letters of ſafe conduct, commonly called Paſſe-ports, and Certificates ſigned by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, or chief Magiſtrate of the Province or City, from whence they come; Of which Letters and Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificates ſuch forms ſhall be obſerved as ſhall be mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually concluded upon, within the ſpace of 4 months, next after the date hereof. And whereſoever any the Merchandize, goods, veſſels, or men belonging to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their People and Subjects, ſhall be met with either in open Sea, or in any Channel, Haven, Road, Land, or any other place by the Ships of War, publick or private, or by any the People, Subjects and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the other, or ſhall happen to be in one place with them, they producing their Letters of ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and Certificates aforeſad, ſhall have nothing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exacted of them, no ſearch made, either of Goods, Veſſels or Men, much leſſe ſhall they receive any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, injury or moleſtation; but ſhall be ſuffered to paſſe on with freedome to purſue their occaſions. And if any People and Subjects of either ſhall do, or commit any thing contrary to the proper ſenſe of this preſent Article, either Confederate ſhall take care that ſevere puniſhment be inflicted on the Offenders, and cauſe full and ſpeedy ſatisfaction to be made to the parties wronged, for all Coſts and Damages.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. In caſe it ſhall hereafter happen, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Amity and Confederation, any of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or ſubjects of either, ſhall act or attempt any thing againſt the ſame or any part thereof, either by Land, Sea, or other waters, this Amity, Confederation and Allyance, ſhall not be thereupon interrupted or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37266:11"/>of, but ſhall remain and continue ſtill in full force and virtue. Onely in ſuch caſe the particular perſons which have offended, ſhall be puniſhed, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; And that Juſtice ſhall be done and ſatisfaction made to all perſons injured, within 12 months after Demand thereof. And in caſe the Perſons ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as aforeſaid ſhall not appear and ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Juſtice, and make ſatisfaction within the ſaid Term, the ſaid Perſons ſhall be declared enemies to both States, and their eſtates, goods and effects whatſoever, ſhall be confiſcated &amp; employed to a due and full ſatisfaction for the wrong by them done. And their perſons ſhall be lyable to further puniſhment when they ſhall come within the power of either State, as the quality of their offence ſhall deſerve. And that ſpeedy reſtitution and ſatisfaction be made for the loſſe and dammage which either part hath ſuſtained from the other, during the War betwixt <hi>England</hi> and the United Provinces.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. This preſent Treaty and Confederation ſhall in nothing derogate from any preeminence, right or Dominion of either Confederate within any his own Seas, Channels or Waters, but that they have and retain the ſame, in as full and ample manner as they have had, or as of right belongs to them.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. It being the primary intent of this League and Amity, that each Confederate their People and Subjects might enjoy ſuch Navigation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, as is deſcribed in the foregoing Articles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Balticke, Sound, Northern, Western,</hi> and <hi>Britiſh Seas, Mediterranean</hi> and <hi>Channel,</hi> and other the Seas in <hi>Europe;</hi> Therefore all ſincere endeavor ſhall be uſed on both ſides by common adviſe, aid and aſſiſtance, that the aforeſaid mutuall Liberty of Navigation and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37266:11"/>commerce, be eſtabliſhed, promoted, and as occaſion is, defended againſt all the Diſturbers thereof, who ſhall go about to interrupt, prohibit, hinder or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and limit the ſame to their own will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in prejudice of the ſaid Confederates. And ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part ſhall with all willingneſſe or readineſs, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the good and prevent the hurt each of other; Saving the Treaties which either Nation hath made with other Kingdoms, Commonwealths &amp; Nations. And neither Confederate ſhall hereafter make any League or Agreement in prejudice of this preſent, with any other People or Nation without the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and conſent of the other, or if any ſuch Agreement be hereafter made, the ſame ſhall be reputed null and voyd, and give place to this preſent Treaty. But as for the manner of giving aid and aſſiſtance each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the defence of this League and of the Liberty of Commerce and Navigation, a more particular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, as need ſhall require, ſhall be made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon accommodated to the Circumſtances of time and other affairs.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. For what concerns other Commodities, which Ships of War may enjoy, and the Laws by which they ſhall regulate themſelves when they ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive in each others Ports and Harbors: and for what concerns commerce to be exerciſed in <hi>America;</hi> as alſo the advantages of the <hi>Herring,</hi> and other Fiſheries, the erecting Staples for Trade, and other Things and Conditions which ſhall be found requiſite for the better clearing of the foregoing Articles, Reſolution ſhall be had therein according to what ſhall be agreed upon in a diſtinct and peculiar Treaty or Contract.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. Whatever is agreed on in the foregoing Articles ſhall be in force and vertue from this preſent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37266:12"/>time, and be truly obſerved on both ſides by all ſuch as are within each others Allegiance. And for the further Confirmation thereof, ſhall be ſubſcribed, ſigned and ratified by the Protector of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions thereto belonging, in the name of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and the ſaid Commonwealth, and by her Majeſty of <hi>Sweden,</hi> under the handwriting and Seals of their ſaid Highneſſe and Majeſty, within four months next enſuing the Date of theſe Preſents.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <head>A <hi>PROCLAMATION</hi> of the Peace made between this Commonwealth, and <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>OLIVER</hi> Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p> Whereas by the bleſſing of God, we have, with the adviſe of our Council, made and concluded a Treaty of Peace, friendſhip, and amity between this Commonwealth on the one part, and <hi>France</hi> on the other, their Lands, Cities, Towns, Dominions, Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, Places, and People, by Sea, Land, freſh-waters, and elſe where; and whereas by the ſaid Treaty of Peace all Acts of Hoſtility are to ceaſe on both ſides immediatly after pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication thereof, as well upon the Sea, as at Land, Rivers, and freſh-waters, and whatever ſhall be taken by the one from the other after the ſaid Publication, ſhall well and truly be restored, and all Letters of Marque and Repriſall to be recalled and made voyd, We have thought fit to make Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, as we doe by theſe preſents, of the aforeſaid Treaty and Agreement; and do hereby ſtrictly charge and require all perſon and perſons, of what degree, quality and condition they, or any of them be, belonging to this Commonwealth, to take notice thereof, and conform themſelves accordingly,
<pb facs="tcp:37266:12"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait enclosed in an oval inscribed in Latin: Louis XIV, by the grace of God most Christian king of Gaul and Navarre; below the oval and its rectangular frame, a tree bearing arrows and other weapons (center) bordered by a Latin motto and flanked by more weapons to the left and right</figDesc>
                  <head>LODOVICVS XIIII.D G. GALLIA ET NAVARRAE REX CHRISTIANISS.</head>
                  <q>VIRTVTI DAMNOSA QVIES</q>
               </figure>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37266:13"/>And in further performance of the ſaid Treaty on our part, we do by theſe preſents require and enjoyn all Ships of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and others belonging to the State, or particular perſons ſet forth upon private Commiſſions, or otherwiſe, to obſerve the ſaid Agreement. And to the end none may pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof, the Commiſſioners of the Admiralty are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required to give effectuall notice of the premiſes to all the Ships of War of this Commonwealth, either at Sea or in Port. And the Judges of the High Court of Admiralty are alſo by virtue of theſe preſents forthwith to call in, upon their ſeverall Securities given in that Court, all ſuch Ships as have been ſet forth upon private Commiſſiions againſt any of the People or Subjects of <hi>France.</hi> 
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>White hall</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>20.</hi> day of <hi>November, 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Here followeth the ſubſtance of the Articles of the Treaty of Peace betwixt <hi>England</hi> &amp; <hi>France.</hi> Nov: <hi>20. 1655.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THat henceforth there be a firm Peace, Amity, and League betwixt the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> and betwixt all the Countries, Dominions, Cities, and Places, within the Dominion of either, and that the People and Subjects of both Nations may freely have recourſe unto all Ports and Havens, without prejudice.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That neither part ſhall hereafter directly or indirectly aſſiſt ſuch as are already declared Rebells or their Adherents; and in caſe either part do make a Peace with ſuch as are already their declared Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that part which ſhall ſo make Peace ſhall not give any aid or aſſiſtance to the ſaid Enemies againſt the other part.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That all Hoſtility ſhall ceaſe henceforth both
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37266:13"/>by Sea and Land, and all Commiſſions and Letters of Marque or Repriſall, iſſued out on both ſides againſt the People and Subjects of either, be recalled. And whatſoever ſhall be taken on either ſide, after the publication of the preſent Treaty, it ſhall be reſtored. And if any injury be done by the People of the one State to the People of the other, no Letters of Marque or Repriſall, ſhall be iſſued out, till juſtice be firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; and in caſe Juſtice cannot be had after the due ways of demand made, then Letters of Marque or Reprizall may be granted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. That freedome of Trade be maintained in all places, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> betwixt the People on both ſides; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that the uſuall Cuſtomes be paid, and the Laws and Statutes of each State be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That the People of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> ſhall have liberty to vend all Manufactures of Wool and Silk made within the ſaid Commonwealth in any place of the Dominion of <hi>France,</hi> notwithſtanding any Law, Edict, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the contrary. Provided, that the 13 Article of the Treaty made between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France, Anno</hi> 1606. concerning Clothes ill made, be kept and obſerved; And that the Subjects of <hi>France</hi> may have free leave to vend all Wines of the growth of <hi>France,</hi> in all ports and places of the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, notwithſtanding any Law or Statute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That the Rates of Cuſtoms, which are to be paid by the Merchants on both ſides, ſhall be hung up in a Table in the publick places at <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Roven,</hi> and in other Cities of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as need ſhall require.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That whereas ſome payments and privileges
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37266:14"/>are claimed by ſome Cities and places, as due unto them, in the Dominions on either ſide, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Officers in all Cities ſhall take care that no more be exacted than what is due.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. That the payment called in Engliſh <hi>Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> in French <hi>Du Chief,</hi> exacted hitherto by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome without Law in ſome Ports of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> ſhall no more be paid by the People of either State, at their entrance or departure.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The French Merchants trading in <hi>England</hi> ſhall not be compelled to put in any other caution for the vending of their Commodities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides their caution upon Oath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. That French Ships may have ſafe recourſe to the Key of <hi>London,</hi> and all other Ports of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> there to take in their lading without moleſtation, and they ſhall not be compelled to unlade into other Veſſells. And the Ships of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſhall enjoy the like liberty in all the Ports of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">XI. That the Merchants Ships of <hi>England,</hi> trading to <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> ſhall not in their paſſage up the River of <hi>Garunne,</hi> be compelled to unlade their Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the Caſtle of <hi>Blaye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">XII. That the Merchants and any other People of the aforeſaid Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> may by Will and Teſtament diſpoſe of their Commodities, money, houſholdſtuffe, Debts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> within all parts of the Dominion of <hi>France,</hi> according to their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And whether they die teſtate or inteſtate, their heirs or executors ſhall enjoy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> in what part of <hi>France</hi> ſoever they ſhall happen to die; and this notwithſtanding the Law commonly called <hi>Droict d'Aubeyne.</hi> The like
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37266:14"/>liberty and privilege is to be enjoyed by the Subjects of <hi>France</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">XIII. That the Inhabitants of the Iſles of <hi>Jerſey</hi> and <hi>Guernſey</hi> ſhall enjoy the ſame privileges and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities in <hi>France</hi> as the French do in thoſe Iſlands, the uſuall Tributes and Cuſtomes being paid on both ſides.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. That for the more eaſie prevention of Pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and injuries to Ships by Rovers at Sea, all Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Maſters in any Men of War, or Ships be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the People of either State, ſhall before they ſet out of any Port within the Dominion of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put in ſecurity for their good behaviour at Sea, and that they will not take or ſeize, nor otherwiſe hinder or injure the people and goods of either. And if thoſe who are appointed to take the Security, ſhall neglect it, or not take good ſecurity, they themſelves ſhall make recompence for ſuch damages as ſhall be done.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. That for the ſpace of 4 years ſucceeding the Ratification of the preſent Treaty, all Ships belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Subjects and People of either State trading in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and in the Eaſtern Sea or Ocean, ſhall be free and have their lading free, although they carry goods in them, yea Grain or Pulſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Enemies; except nevertheleſſe all prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Contraband goods, that is to ſay Gunpowder, Guns, Piſtols, and all ſorts of Arms, Munition, Horſes and Warlike Proviſion, nor ſhall they tranſport men for the ſervice of the Enemies of either State, in caſe the Ships, Proviſion and Goods ſhall become Prize; which ſhall be ſeverely put in execution alſo againſt ſuch as ſhall carry Corn or Victualls for relief of places beſieged by either State.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37266:15"/>
            <p n="16">XVI. That both Parties ſhall expreſly charge their Sea Commanders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That they doe not any way prejudice or hinder the People of either State in their Ships, Veſſels, Goods or Merchandize, but dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently obſerve this Treaty; And that thoſe who violate it, ſhall beſide the undergoing of Corporall puniſhment, repaire the Damages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that ſuch men of War, as being deſigned Convoy to Merchant men, ſhall meet with Veſſells belonging to either State, be obliged to defend them againſt any that ſhall offer violence, ſo long as they hold the ſame courſe together.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. The ſeventeenth Article enjoyneth the copying out and ſecuring of Books of Accounts, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Bills of lading, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That ſhall be found in any Ships, belonging to the People of either State, that may happen to be made Prize by any of the Sea Commanders of either Party, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. The eighteenth concerns ſuch Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Maſters, Mariners and Seamen, taken in Veſſels that ſhall be made Prize as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. That neither of the Confederates ſhall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour or permit their People to harbour any Pyrates or Robbers, nor to aſſiſt or ſupply them, but rather endeavor to apprehend and bring them to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved puniſhment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">XX That neither of the ſaid Parties doe permit that the Ships or Goods belonging to either people, which ſhall at any time be taken by the Rebells of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon pretence, or by vertue of any Commiſſion whatſoever, and be brought into the Ports or Places of either Dominion, be alienated from the right Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but they ſhall be detained and laid up ſafe, that no part of them periſh or be imbeliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:37266:15"/>
            <p n="21">XXI. That if the People of either part ſhall be driven by Tempeſt, fear of Enemies, or any other dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, into the Ports of either Nation, they ſhall depart free without paying any Cuſtome or Tribute, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they neither buy nor ſell there, &amp; do at their firſt coming give an Account of their Arrivall to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of the Place.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. That the People of the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth may freely Trade in all Kingdoms, Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Territories, that are in Amity or Neutrality with the ſaid Commonwealth, and not be hindred or injured by the ſubjects of the ſaid King, although there ſhould be an enmity and Hoſtility betwixt the ſaid King, and thoſe Kingdomes, Dominions and Territories, or any of them. The ſame is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in like manner, on the ſaid Commonwealths part towards the ſubjects of <hi>France.</hi> Provided that neither of them do Trade to any port or Town beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by either party, nor carry any prohibited Goods unto ſuch places as are in hoſtility with either, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. That inpartial Juſtice be done to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of either, according as by the rule of Law &amp; Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all Cauſes depending on eithers Dominion, and that all Sentences, and former Bargains and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made by the people of either, for their own advantage, do ſtand good, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. And foraſmuch as ſince the year 1640 many prizes have been taken, and many damages done by the people of each nation to one another, it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That there Commiſſioners be nominated im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Ratification of the preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with power to examine, eſtimate, and clear ſuch Prizes and Lawes, and determine the compenſation and ſatisfaction for them, according to the demands,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37266:16"/>which ſhall be produced and exhibited before them, by their people on either part, within three months time, to be accounted after the publication of this Treaty; For which purpoſe the ſaid Commiſſioners are to meet within ſix weeks after publication, in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and to determine the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies within five months next following. And if within ſix months they ſhall not agree, then the ſaid controverſies ſhall be referred to the arbitration of the republick of <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> to be determited with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four months time next after, who are deſired to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point Commiſſioners to give Judgment upon the premiſes, and whatſoever they ſhall determine ſhall be binding to both Parties, and ſhall be performed within 6 months next following. And if theſe ſhall not determine the ſaid Controverſie, then no man ſhall be moleſted thereupon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">XXV. That the Controverſie betwixt both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties touching the Forts of <hi>Pemtacoet, St. John,</hi> and <hi>Port Royal,</hi> lately taken in <hi>America,</hi> and the goods found in them, be referred to the aforeſaid Commiſſioners and Arbitrators mentioned in the fore-going Article.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. That if there ſhould happen to be a war be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſaid Commonwealth and Kingdome, the Merchants living in Towns and Cities ſhall have ſix months time after the declaring of the War to ſell and tranſport their Goods and Comodities, and if any da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or injury be done them by the people of either part, they ſhall have recompence and ſatiſfaction gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. If it ſo fall out, that during this League and Amity any thinge ſhall be done by any of the people on either ſide, contrary thereto, this League and Amity ſhall notwithſtanding remain entire, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37266:16"/>retain its full force, but the perſons ſo offending ſhall be puniſhed and ſatiſfaction given to all parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. That this Treaty ſhall within 15 daies next following be confirmed and ratified under the great Seal of both Nations, and the inſtruments be delivered on both ſides, and afterwards this preſent Treaty ſhall be publiſhed in the accuſtomed place and manner.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A Relation of Gen: <hi>Blakes</hi> engagement with the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Tunnis:</hi> And of their ſubmiſſion in <hi>Argier.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two sailing ships in battle, with a smaller boat in the foreground</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Tunnis</hi> Road, <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 9. 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>AFter the <hi>Turks</hi> in <hi>Tunnis</hi> had given us an unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied anſwer, we ſailed to them again, and arrived
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37266:17"/>at <hi>Porta Ferina</hi> the 3 of <hi>April;</hi> when we came there the Officers met, and we ſought to the Lord by Prayer, after which the Officers met in Counſel, and that day it was unanimouſly reſolved by the Generalls and Captains, to ſet upon the Turks Ships there the next day, and to burn them. On the 4 of <hi>April</hi> we cauſed the Turks to flie before us, their Caſtle of <hi>Porta Ferina</hi> we battered, their ſtrong Town and houſes of ſtone we did beat about their ears: By break of day the whole fleet weighed anchor; The <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> Frigot went firſt in, after her the <hi>Kent,</hi> the <hi>Taunton,</hi> the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fight,</hi> the <hi>Amity, Princeſſe-Maria, Pearl, Mearmaid,</hi> and <hi>Merlin</hi> followed, and came to anchor neer the Turks 9 Ships who lay cloſe to the Caſtle and Forts by it: Then came in the <hi>Andrew</hi> our Vice-Admirall, and the <hi>Plimouth,</hi> after them the <hi>George, Worcester, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn, Bridgwater,</hi> and <hi>Succeſſe,</hi> theſe all anchored juſt againſt the Body of the Caſtle within musket ſhot, and began to play our broad ſides of Guns at the Caſtle, which we plyed very thick for 4 or 5 hours; In the mean while our other Frigots ſent their boats aboard the Ships to endeavor the firing of them, which by the bleſſing of God was done by 11 a clock; we had hot work of it, for their Ships lay within Piſtoll ſhot of the ſhore, and all the Coaſt was lined with Musketeirs, and about 60 pieces of Ordnance mounted upon the Caſtle. The moſt men ſlain were in the Boats going aboard their Ships, which was by ſmall ſhot, 30 is the moſt to be ſlain in the whole Fleet, and about 80 wounded; which conſidering the ſtrength of the Place, and the many advantages the Turks had upon us, was but a ſmall number. We are now in <hi>Tunnis</hi> Road, and Generall <hi>Blake</hi> hath ſent once more a ſhore, but what will be done we know not.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37266:17"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>April</hi> 10. 1655. The Turks in <hi>Argier</hi> do conſent to deliver up all the Engliſh that they have ſlaves, to Generall <hi>Blake,</hi> and declare that they deſire a Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Peace with <hi>England,</hi> and that the Lord Protector will ſend a Councill to them, to make a firm Peace with them for ever. And it is believed that <hi>Tripilo</hi> will do the like.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Pope Alexander VII (?)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>To our Venerable Brethren, The Patriarchs, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Clergi-men, Religious, and all the Faithfull ones of Christ belonging to the Catholick Church.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>ALEXANDER VII. <hi>POPE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>VEnerable Brethern, beloved Sons, greeting, and Apoſtolicall Benediction.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>While from the height of our Apoſtolick Dignity we look round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, and ſollicitouſly ſurvey the State of Things
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37266:18"/>throughout the World, as ſubjected to our Care and Charge, the Affairs of Chriſtendom appear to be in a very ſad and lamentable condition; for ſtrangers make ſpoil of the Portion of the Lord, and his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, caſting out thoſe that are indeed his Children. Thoſe Nations, which out of our Fatherly love and tenderneſſe, we had a deſire to take into our boſom, that is to ſay, into the boſom of true Religion, and moſt affectionately to embrace them, even they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to rend and tear this very boſome in pieces; and making their way from the remoteſt parts of ſea and land, have invaded the Flock of Chriſt. Yea and Catholick Princes diſagreeing bend their Forces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, and (which is a Judgement that God threatned heretofore againſt our Enemies, and them that riſe up againſt us) they devour one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and are made drunk with their own Blood, as it were with new wine. Whilſt in time paſt, we were ſilently bewayling theſe things with our ſelf, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good to him, who works things great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible without number, to call us, unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and trembling, to the Goverment of the Church; and to lay this immenſe burthen upon us, enough to make the ſtrongeſt ſhoulders to ſhrink. What our ſorrow hath been, we have teſtified by thoſe publick prayers, which we enjoyned in all parts, as ſoon as we were advanced to the Supremacie; as alſo by thoſe Letters which we ſent to our moſt dear Sons, not onely to the Illuſtrious <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi> King, and Roman Emperor Elect, but alſo to the 2 Kings, and which with griefe of heart we wrote a ſecond time, when we perceived our moſt deadly Enemy deſigning ruine and deſtruction to all <hi>Europe,</hi> by diſtreſſing the moſt renowned Republick,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37266:18"/>to the end that we might turn them from mutuall diſcords, againſt ſo dangerous an Adverſary; and now alſo we ſend againe, admoniſhing them, that whilſt their Armies are at a ſtand, during this winter ſeaſon, they would uſe their utmoſt endeavor to ſettle Peace. Let all theſe things bear witneſſe for us, that ſeeing there remains no hope to mittigate ſo great and ſore evills, ſave onely in common concord, it is the main care that takes up our Mind night and day, to inſinuate it into the hearts and affections of all men. But becauſe this is not to be effected by humane ſtrength and earthly wiſdome, but ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from him as his gift, upon whom reſts the diſcipline of our Peace, who takes away the Spirit of Princes, and rebuketh the Sea, and it is Still; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe you <hi>(Venerable Brethren, and Beloved Sons)</hi> ſtrive as much as in you lies, not onely by your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, ſtudy, Counſel, duties, and Authority, but alſo rent your hearts in prayer, in tears, in faſtings, and Alms deeds, take ye the Cenſor of Incenſe, that is, the prayer of the Saints; and ſtand ye in the gap be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Fire, and the people that are ready to be conſumed. You who are ſet to be watchmen upon the walls of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> cry aloud night and day, and be ye the Appeaſers of divine wrath and vengeance. Empty out the Cup of Fury and deſtruction, the Cup of anguiſh and of tribulation without mixture, with which we have been drunken. We for our part, to whom Chriſt thought not his ſheep ſafely commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, till we were again and the third time admoniſhed in <hi>Peter</hi> touching the greatneſſe of his Love, to whom alone it is given to enter the Sanctuary, and to preſent the prayers of the people to God before the Altar, conceive it our duty with all diligence
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37266:19"/>to labour, that the Lord may not be angry, and ſay, <hi>I ſought a man to make up the Breach, and to plead with me for the earth, that I might not deſtroy it, and I found him not, therefore have I powred out mine indignation upon them.</hi> For this is the property of divine vengeance, that he who is the moſt high, is then moſt eaſie to be entreated, and returns to gentleneſſe and mercy, that is, to his own nature, when he draweth the ſword with his mighty Arm and ſtrong hand, to the end that he may ſtrike. Let your Feet be the Feet of thoſe that bring the glad Tidings of the Goſpell of Peace, that the Bowes and Arrows may be broken in pieces, and that God may command the winds, and cauſe Peace and Tranquility; which by your aſſiſtance eſpecially we deſire to obtain, and doe moſt affectionately confer upon you our Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Benediction.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at <hi>Rome,</hi> in St. <hi>Mary</hi> the Greater, under the <hi>ſeal-ring of the Fiſher,</hi> 
                  <date>the 20 of <hi>September,</hi> 1655. In the firſt year of our Popedom.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>NATALIS RONDININ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter concerning the manner of the Queen of <hi>Swedens</hi> renouncing her Religion, and imbracing the Popiſh, written by an eye-witneſſe, </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>at <hi>Inſpruck</hi> in <hi>Tiroll, <date>October 26. 1655.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shall acquaint you with the manner of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> into this City. The Archduke of <hi>Tirol</hi> having many months ſince been advertiſed of the Queens intention, to paſſe through this City, reſolved to give her an extraordinary noble entertainment. To this end he ſent Letters to all the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37266:19"/>Gentry and Nobility in this Country, and to his Friends in the parts adjacent, to wait upon him in their bravery at his Court on Saturday laſt. In the evening the Archduke having intelligence that the Queen would lodge within 9 mile of this City, took Poſt with his brother the Archbiſhop, and a dozen Gentlemen, and onely kiſt her hands, bidding her welcom into his Dominions, and returned back hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame night. The next day, being Sunday, about 4 in the afternoon, 12 of the Archdukes Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petters, and moſt of the aforeſaid Nobility and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try rode before him, the Archdutcheſs, which is the Duke of <hi>Florence</hi> his Siſter, being carried after him in a rich Sedan, the reſt of the Gentry about and behind her; then followed his Guard on Horſback, being 50 Firelocks, his ordirnary Guard with Halberts ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on each ſide of the way: and in this equipage he met the Queen about a mile from the City; about 20 yeards before he came at her he light off his horſe, and ſhe out of her Sedan, and ſaluted one another; and ſo in the former manner, with Trumpets, Drums, and other loud Muſick very fine, ſhe entred the City.</p>
            <p>The next day I ſaw her at dinner onely with the Archduke, his Lady, and Brother, which was very magnificent: I made account to have ſeen her at ſupper, but ſhe ſupped privately; yet being at the Court, I was told, That the Queen the next day would make open profeſſion of the Catholick Faith in the Franciſcans or Archdukes Chappell, which not onely I, but all her Proteſtant Servants much admired at, and would not believe; but it proved true: For on the Wedneſday between a 11 and 12 of clock, ſhe was led to the aforeſaid Church
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37266:20"/>by the Archduke, attended by the company afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, and ſeated upon a Canopy on the left hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the High Alter; below her, a little toward her right hand, was the Archduke, and his Lady, and Brother; and over againſt them the Spaniſh Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador in a Chair by himſelfe; all the Quire being hung with Crimſon Velvet, and the ground covered with red Serge: Then Mr. <hi>Holſtenius,</hi> who was ſent as the Popes Nuntio, ſtood at the right ſide of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſaid, That Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII, having underſtood that <hi>Chriſtina</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the Holy Ghoſt, had intent to put her ſelf into the boſom of the Church, had ſent his Letters to teſtifie his Approbation of her deſires, and to receive her with his Apoſtolicall Benediction, therefore he was there to know, whether it were true or not; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſhe made anſwer, that it was ſo. Then he gave the Popes Letter to a Prieſt that ſtood by, who red it aloud to the effect aboveſaid; the Letter being read, Mr. <hi>Holſtenius</hi> deſired that in Teſtimony of the truth, ſhe would make Profeſſion of the ſaid Catholick Apoſtolick, and Roman Faith, and ſwear to keep it upon the Holy Evangeliſts, before the Archduke and the Spaniſh Ambaſſodor, which ſhe did, and kiſſed the Book. Then was a Chair for <hi>Holſtenius</hi> to ſit in, and a Cuſhion laid at his Feet, upon which the Queen kneeled, and he making the ſign of the Croſſe over her head, and embracing her ſhoulders, ſaid, That he did receive her into the Catholick Church, and by virtue of Order from the Holy Father, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII, and from power given by Chriſt, whoſe Vicar he was, he did abſolve her from all her ſins that ſhe had committed, In the Name of the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then were certain ſhort Prayers ſaid (or rather ſung) in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37266:20"/>Latine for her; after which, High Maſſe was ſung, and then a Prieſt made a Sermon in Dutch, his Text was out of the <hi>Pſalms. Hear O my Daughter, incline alſo thine ear, forget alſo thy people and thy Fathers houſe; ſo ſhall the King have pleaſure in thy Beauty.</hi> Then was <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſung with moſt excellene Voices; and fifty peeces of Ordnance diſcharged, and ſo ſhe retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home as ſhe came.</p>
            <div type="profession">
               <head type="illustration">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>portrait of Christina, Queen of Sweden (?)</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <head>The Profeſſion of Faith of <hi>Chriſtina</hi> Queen of <hi>Swedland,</hi> as it was publiquely Sworn unto at <hi>Inſpruck.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. I Doe firmly admit and embrace Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Eccleſiaſticall Traditions, and the other Obſervances and Conſtitutions of the Church. Alſo I admit the holy Scriptures according to that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37266:21"/>ſence which our holy Mother the Church, to whom it belongs to judge of the true ſence and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of holy Scriptures, hath held, and doth hold: neither will I ever take and interpret it but according to the unanimous conſent of the Fathers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. I doe profeſſe alſo that there be truly and properly ſeven Sacraments of the new Law inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and neceſſary to the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind, though all be not neceſſary for every man; that is to ſay, Baptiſm, Confirmation, the Euchariſt, Penance, Extream unction, Order, and Matrimony; and that they confer grace: and of theſe Baptiſm, Confirmation and Order cannot be reiterated without Sacriledge: Alſo the received and approved Rites of the Catholick Church uſed in the ſolemn adminiſtration of all the aforeſaid Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I receive and admit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. All and every the things which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined and declared in the holy Councill of <hi>Trent</hi> concerning Originall ſinne and Juſtification I em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. I profeſſe alſo that in the Maſſe there is offred unto God a true, proper, and propitiatory Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the quick and dead: and that in the moſt holy Sacrament of the Euchariſt, there is truly, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and ſubſtantially, the Body and Blood, together with the Soul and Divinity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and there is made a converſion of the whole ſubſtance of the bread into the Body, and of the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the wine into the Blood, which converſion the Catholick Church calls Tranſubſtantiation: I confeſſe alſo that under either ſole ſpecies, all and whole Chriſt, and a true Sacrament is received.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. I doe hold there is a Purgatory, and that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37266:21"/>Souls therein detained, are holpen by the ſuffrages of the faithfull. Alſo, that the Saints reigning with Chriſt, are to be worſhipped and prayed unto, and that they offer prayers to God for us, and that their Relicks are to be worſhipped: I moſt firmly avouch that the Images of Chriſt, and of the mother of God, always a Virgin, and of other Saints alſo, are to be had and retained, and that due honor and veneration is to be given them. Alſo I affirm that the power of Indulgences was left by Chriſt in the Church, and that the uſe of them is moſt wholſome to Chriſtian people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. I acknowledge the holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Roman Church Mother and Miſtreſſe of all Churches, and I promiſe and ſwear true obedience to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſucceſſor to St. <hi>Peter</hi> Prince of the Apoſtles, and Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt: I doe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe undoubtedly receive and profeſſe all other things delivered, defined, and declared by the ſacred Canons and Councills oecumenicall and particularly by the holy Councill of <hi>Trent;</hi> and withall I do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, reject, and anathematize all things that are contrary thereunto, and all Hereſies whatſoever the Church hath condemned, rejected, &amp; anathematized. And I do promiſe, vow and ſwear, that I will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to hold and confeſſe conſtantly (with Gods help) this true Catholick Faith, out of which no man can be ſaved, which at this preſent I do willingly profeſs and truly holds; and alſo as far as I am able, that by thoſe who are under me, or over whom by reaſon of my charge, I ſhall have care it be held taught and profeſſed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>CHRISTINA R.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37266:22"/>
            <head>A brief Deſcription of the Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> and a Relation of poſſeſſing the Town of St. <hi>Jago de la Viga,</hi> with the Routing the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies from their Forts and Ordnance, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſaid Iſland, <hi>May 10. 1655.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>COncerning <hi>Jamica</hi> or <hi>Jamaica,</hi> we find theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing paſſages heretofore. In the Navigation of <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus, cap.</hi> 98. <hi>Tandem Admirans devenit ad Inſulam, quam Inſulam Jamicam, &amp;c.</hi> The Admirall at length came to an Iſland which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants call <hi>Jamica:</hi> This Iſland is as fruitfull as any place near the Sea coaſts or within the Land.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Peter Martyr, dec.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>Eſt his Auſtralior Jamai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, &amp;c. Jamaica</hi> is a little more Southerly then <hi>Cuba</hi> and <hi>Hiſpaniola;</hi> it is a pleaſant and fruitfull Iſland, moſt happy in the fertility of ſoil, and it hath but one Mountain, and is moſt fit for ſowing.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Dec.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>Hanc inſulam Siciliam longiorem latioremque praedicat:</hi> It is ſaid that this Iſland is greater then <hi>Sicily.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>map of the Caribbean, including Cuba, Jamaica, Hispaniola, and many smaller islands, and some of the surrounding coastlines (tip of Florida, north coast of South America, and a bit of the east coast of southernmost North America)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Deſcription of the American Iſlands, ſaith of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> It is in length from Eaſt to Weſt about 50 leagues, and in breadth 20, the whole compaſſe eſtimated at 150. The middle of it under the 18 Degree of Northern latitude: of a rich Soil, abundantly provided of all things neceſſary, well ſtocked with cattell, and no leſſe plentifully ſtored with moſt ſorts of fruits, which either induſtry or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have ſupplyed it with; great ſtore of Cotton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wool, and ſuch a bundance of Jaccu (a Root where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Savages once made their bread) that it was deemed the Granary of the neighboring Iſlands.</p>
            <p>The Iſland <hi>Jamaica</hi> belongeth properly to the Duke of <hi>Veragus,</hi> who is lineally deſcended from <hi>Christopher Columbus,</hi> the Diſcoverer of the Indies, and not to the Duke of <hi>Medina,</hi> as was by ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>The chief Ports of this Iſland are (1) <hi>Caguaya</hi> which ſerves to the Town of St. <hi>Jago de la Vega,</hi> or St. <hi>James</hi> of the Plains, from whence it is about two leagues diſtant.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Port of any note on that Southſide, is <hi>Eſquyvel,</hi> which is about three leagues diſtant from the former towards the Weſt, which though the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell be, as of the former, difficult to find, is within a commodious Haven; and in reſpect of an Arm of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37266:23"/>the Sea which affords the Commodity of building of Shipping; within it is of ſingular commodity to the Iſland. This Arm of the Sea extends it ſelfe a full league within the Land, where it admits into it a ſmall freſh Brook, called <hi>Ell Rio de la Puente,</hi> which ariſing within two leagues of the Town of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> and paſſing pleaſantly through the <hi>Savanas,</hi> is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Arm before deſcribed, which is called <hi>Guavayera.</hi> The Land between the Town of St. <hi>Jago</hi> and this place, is for the moſt part open, and <hi>Savana</hi> land, well ſtored with cattell and horſes. From thence to <hi>Maccario,</hi> which is about ſix leagues diſtant the Coaſt, is good and fit for Anchoring; but affords no Port or Harbour nearer then <hi>Panda Botellio,</hi> which is a round Mountain, about a league to the Weſt of which, a River called <hi>Mantineſſe</hi> diſcharges it ſelfe into the Sea: This River ariſes about a league, or a league and halfe with the land, and abounds in fiſh, and is well ſtored with cattell, upon the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hatos,</hi> and <hi>Savanas</hi> of <hi>Tama</hi> and <hi>Guatibacoa.</hi> Thence paſſing along this Coaſt, the next place of goodneſſe of Land, or conveniency of Anchoring. And about eight leagues diſtant from <hi>Peccaria,</hi> is <hi>Punta de la Goſtus,</hi> which is in the Hato of <hi>Perada,</hi> which is one of the beſt and largeſt pieces of <hi>Savana</hi> of the whole Iſland, it being four leagues in length and more.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Pereda</hi> to <hi>Elconde,</hi> another little Port is five leagues, between which two places falls into the Sea the great River <hi>Caphana,</hi> which ariſing in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, paſſes through <hi>Savanas</hi> of the ſame name, well ſtored with cattell; and leaving the open land about a league from the Sea, runs through wooddy and manguey, or mountainous grounds, and is from the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37266:24"/>very <hi>Savana,</hi> of depth ſufficient for moſt ordinary Ships, but narrow, as being over grown by the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groves, for want of uſe or clearing; yet contains in the narroweſt about ſixty or ſeventy foot of breadth. At the mouth this River receives into it certain large Brooks of freſh water; but of no other conſideration then for fiſhing onely, whereof it affords a plentifull commodity. The mouth of this River, by reaſon of the ſmalneſſe of its fall, is barred with the ſands, ſo that unleſſe at ſome times of conſiderable flouds, it hath not depth above four foot upon the Bar, but without is Anchoring good enough in the open Road, but harbour none at all.</p>
            <p>Next about two leagues diſtant, is <hi>El Eaido,</hi> which is a <hi>Hata,</hi> having ſome ſmall <hi>Savanas,</hi> but very great plenty of cattell abiding in the Woods, which the Spaniards call <hi>Ganadus Siniarones,</hi> or wild cattell, as being not marked, nor belonging to any certaine proprietor, other then the chief Lord and owner of the <hi>Hato.</hi> In this <hi>Hato</hi> is a ſmall Port called <hi>Puto del Conde,</hi> of no great value or conſideration.</p>
            <p>Thence to <hi>Punto Negrillio,</hi> is no other Port or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour whatſoever; but paſſing by land, is a <hi>Hato</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cabnico,</hi> large and well ſtored with cattell, both wild and tame.</p>
            <p>Thence next is called the <hi>Savana</hi> of the Sea, which reaches to the Cape <hi>Negrillio.</hi> From the <hi>Puerto de Cuguaya</hi> towards the Eaſt, is the <hi>Hato de Loguany,</hi> which is at the Eaſt ſide of the Port it ſelfe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to the Harbour a large and well ſtored <hi>Savana,</hi> with an Arm of the Port extending to it, commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the building of Shipping, there being ſtore both of Cedars and other ſort of Timber convenient for that purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37266:24"/>
            <p>Next Eaſtward Land to this of <hi>Lyguany,</hi> is <hi>Lezania,</hi> a narrow tract of plantable land between the ſea and the mountain, containing ſome ſmall Savanas, but no habitation, nor any Cattell but wild, and is about two leagues in length.</p>
            <p>Then is the <hi>Hato Ayala</hi> full of tame cattle, and hath much commodity of planting, or erecting of Sugar Engenios of water, by reaſon of two convenient Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers which it hath running through, is fit for that purpoſe; but is dangerouſly open to the incurſion of Pirats, who there have too much commodity of landing in two ſmall Cores or Bighs of Land, the one of which is called <hi>los Anaones,</hi> towards the Weſt of this <hi>Hato,</hi> and to the Eaſt <hi>la Cruz del Padre.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Severall ſorts of Wood in this Country.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Grandillio,</hi> of a reddiſh black colour, and heavy as Ebony, uſed much in theſe parts for bedſteads.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Cedar,</hi> the beſt in all the Indies, uſefull for all purpoſes, as Oake in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Cawobena,</hi> a Tree of ſix fathome about, a fine red, excellent good for beds, tables, or buildings.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Cittano,</hi> of a yellow colour, a fathome about, excellent for dying, called in Engliſh, yellow Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Braſil,</hi> and <hi>Braſiletto,</hi> excellent for dying, ſold in theſe parts at one pound ſeventeen ſhillings and ſix pence <hi>per</hi> hundred.</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Guaicum,</hi> good for bedſteads, bowls and chairs, and Phyſicians uſes, three foot over, ſold at <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena</hi> for two ſhillings <hi>per</hi> pound.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37266:25"/>
               <head>The Country affords ſeverall Fruits.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Pepper ſmelling like Cloves, the North ſide of the Iſland is full of it, wild, good for Chocolatto, ſold here at ſix pence <hi>per</hi> pound. The Leaf diſtilled, makes excellent good water, much eſteemed by the Spaniards at <hi>Carthagena.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Pyne, the beſt that ever was eat, in ſeaſon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the year long, ſold at ſix pence <hi>per</hi> piece.</item>
                  <item>3. Niſpero, eſteemed the beſt fruit in the Indies by the Spaniards, in ſeaſon in <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Mameſappole, taſtes like Marmalet, in ſeaſon part of <hi>June, July,</hi> and <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. Avocatas, a wholſome pleaſant fruit; in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſold for eight pence <hi>per</hi> piece.</item>
                  <item>6. Cocao, in great plenty, of which they make Chocolatto, ſold ordinarily for three ſhillings <hi>per</hi> buſhell.</item>
                  <item>7. Catrao, a very ſweet luſcious fruit, green of colour, and much like a Mulberry in ſhape and bigneſſe.</item>
                  <item>8. Limes, Limons, Oranges, Guavers, Bonana's, Plantan's, Papaas, Melons of all ſorts, and very good Cucumbers, Gourds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the largeſt Potatoes ever eye beheld.</item>
                  <item>9. Tobacco, which at <hi>Carthagena</hi> bears the beſt Rate there.</item>
                  <item>10. Indico.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:37266:25"/>
               <head>The ſubſtance of divers Letters from the Generalls and Commiſſioners in the Weſt-Indies to his Highnes, to the effect following.</head>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Aug: 8. 1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE left <hi>Barbadoes</hi> the laſt of <hi>March,</hi> and came to St. <hi>Christophers,</hi> where we found a Regiment formed, which we received into our company, not ſtaying to anchor. Thence paſſing forward, we came in ſight of <hi>Sancta Luz, Porto Rico,</hi> and ſome other I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and on ther 3 of <hi>April</hi> arived before <hi>Sancto Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingo,</hi> part of our forces landing within ſix miles of the Town, without any oppoſition, but the main of the Army landed near 40 miles beyond it, contrary to what was intended; which fell out in reſpect of the abſence of the Pilot, who being ſent out to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, returned not in time. This occaſioned a very long march for the Army through Woods and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Lanes, and all without any guide; which with the heate of the weather, and want of water, put the Army into ſome weakneſſe and diſtemper, and made them very unfit for ſervice. The Souldiers likewiſe ſtragled from their Colours to gather Oranges, Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Pines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the extraordinary eating whereof put many of them into the Flux, and Feavers. In this condition we advanced near the Town, where our forelorn, being ſurpriſed by an Ambuſh, and their Leader Adjurant Generall <hi>Jackson</hi> running away, were put to a retreat by 300 men; and there Major Generall <hi>Heans</hi> keeping his ground, was ſlain. This Ambuſcado was afterwards routed by ſome of the Sea-men, who came up to relieve the Forlorn. <hi>Iack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was caſhiered for cowardize, and had his ſword broken over his head.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:37266:26"/>
                  <p>After this, the Army retreating for ſome refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it was thought moſt convenient by the Officers, and moſt for the ſervice, to leave that Iland (the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being weakned by their aforeſaid long march) and to attempt the Iland of <hi>Iamaica:</hi> And having ſhipped the Army, we arived there uppon the 10 of <hi>May,</hi> and took the Town of <hi>St. Iago de la Vega,</hi> having beat the Enemy from their Forts and Ordnance, who were got together in a body, conſiſting of about 3000 men. And from this place nothing did divert our firſt atrempt, but that it had not a name in the world; for we find the Country equall, if not ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and in four miles march here, we ſaw more Cattle and Plantations then in fourty in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and a better aire; and the ſcituation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of much more advantagious to all purpoſes. We are now getting horſes, whereof there are great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance in the Iſland to make Troopers and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, to purſue the Enemy, who are fled unto the Woods, and endeavour to get away into the Iſland of <hi>Cuba,</hi> twenty leagues from this; for prevention whereof we have laid ſome Frigots in the way. The Fleet got ſafe into the Harbor, which is indeed a very ſafe and gallant one for riding in all winds. We find here Ebony in great plenty, ſtore of large Cattle, and Timber in abundance for ſhipping, and ſome ſhips on the ſtocks in building; the Ground very Fertile, and full of brave Plains and Rivers. There is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe great ſtore of Salt-Peter, which ſome men among us, who are Powder men of <hi>London,</hi> doe affirme, may be had as good and as plentifully, as in any place in the world, and in three years time they will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to ſerve <hi>England</hi> with it, woods and Rivers for carriage being eaſie here, with choice places to erect
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37266:26"/>Mills. We want onely workme, ſome of our men are already beginning to Plant.</p>
                  <p>We loſt in <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> between two and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men by ſickneſſe and Skirmiſhes with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and killed in the Woods by the Cow-killers, as they were ſtragling to gather fruit. The Town where our Army is, is a well built Town of Stone and Brick, above two miles about, and is able to Quarter 20000 men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Septemb: 23. 1655.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <head>Came the following Intelligence touching Gen: <hi>Pen,</hi> Gen: <hi>Venables,</hi> and our affairs in the Weſt-Indies.</head>
                  <p>GEnerall <hi>Pen</hi> arrived at the <hi>Spit</hi>-head near <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> with part of the Fleet, the 31 of the laſt month, having left a very good Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron behind him in thoſe Seas, and being come as far as the <hi>Havana</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Cuba,</hi> the Ship <hi>Paragon</hi> fell on fire by negligence, and ſo periſhed in the Sea, blowing up many of the men that were in her. The ſaid Gen: <hi>Pen</hi> is not yet come to <hi>London,</hi> but hath ſent hither Letters which he brought from Gen: <hi>Venables.</hi> There are 20 ſail returned, and 13 left behind: And that notwithſtanding ſome diſcouragements at firſt in that part of the world, yet now our men are well accommodated, and doubt not but to bring good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Commonwealth by their Expedition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>The Letter from Gen: <hi>Venables</hi> to a perſon of Honour.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce my laſt of the ſixth of this inſtant, we have taken ſome priſoners of the enemy; the reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Mountains, wanting houſes, bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:37266:27"/>willing to ſubmit, if not overawed by a few amongſt them, yet we hope to make them good Subjects, moſt of them being <hi>Portugais,</hi> and ſhall endeavour to gaine them by our civility. That which we moſt want for the preſent, is bread and Bandry, there being not much <hi>Caſava</hi> in the Country, and of that the enemies ſteal a ſhare, but we ſhall be planting more of that, and hope our Friends will give us a ſupply aſſoon as may be. There be ſome conſiderations and expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents which will be ſent into <hi>England,</hi> not yet fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon; and I am not able now to enlarge, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving quite ſpent my ſpirits; but this Iſland <hi>Jamaica,</hi> for Commodities, Aire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in ſcituation for other purpoſes, exceedeth <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>
                        <hi>your very obliged Servant,</hi> ROB: VENABLES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>Here followeth another Letter from the Fleet in <hi>Jamaica</hi> Harbour, concerning our Affairs in the Weſt-Indies.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>June 25. 1656.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IN the laſt to you dated the 12 of <hi>March,</hi> by the conveyance of the <hi>Grantham,</hi> we intimated the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of ſome Frigats for the Maine, which ſince returned with Intelligence onely of 7 ſhips in the Harbour of <hi>Carthagene.</hi> A few dayes after, A Council of War was called, and it was thought expedient to move upon ſome deſigne for the advantage of the Commonwealth rather than lie ſtill in Harbour. In order to which, eleven of the beſt ſailing Frigats in the Fleet were choſen out for the effecting of our purpoſe (the Admiral himſelf to command in chief.)
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37266:27"/>The Port we were bound for, proved to be <hi>Rio de la Hache,</hi> a Town about 30 Leagues to the Eaſtward of <hi>Sancta Martha.</hi> We landed 500 Seamen a mile Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Town, where they ſaluted us from the Fort ſtanding to the Eaſtward with three great ſhot, but did no execution; whereupon we marched boldly forward, and by the advantage of ſome houſes near adjoyning, we got thither, and played our ſmall ſhot into the Fort ſo faſt, that they ſoon deſerted their great Gunns, and begged for Quarter, which was preſently granted; the Fort was 19 foot high, with a Breſt-work on the top, and 4 braſſe Guns mounted: The Inhabitants had ſent away all their Goods by their Negroes upon their firſt eſpiall of us, which was 5 hours before we landed. We ſtayed there 3 or 4 days, and ſent ſeverall Parties up into the Country in queſt of the Enemy, but took none ſave one Frier, and ſome Spaniſh women and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groes. In the mean time, ſeverall came down with Flags of Truce, and gave us notice, that the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the place would come and compound for them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but they failed at the prefixed time; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Orders were given for carrying aboard the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh priſoners (women excepted) and the Town to be immediately fired, and our Forces drawn off.</p>
                  <p>After all matters were diſpatched here, we ſet ſail to <hi>Sancta Martha</hi> to review our former ſpoiles. We drew out the ſame party, and went on ſhore, no Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my oppoſing, moſt perſons of Quality being fled to <hi>Carthagene</hi> for ſecurity. We ſoon left the place after we had watered; and eſpying a Saile at Sea, in few hours we came up with her, and found her to be a Spaniſh Prize laden with Oyle, Olives, Wine, Stuffs, to a good value.</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37266:28"/>
                  <p>Then we moved towards <hi>Carthagene</hi> to ſhew our ſelves; we lay there one day, and then 8 of the Fleet departed for <hi>Jamaica,</hi> leaving three of us behind in our former ſtation, 6 leagues Eaſtward of <hi>Carthagene.</hi> In their way they chaſed another Ship laden with Cocoes, and took her, and have ſent the Fruit to the Lord Protector: it is good to make Chocolette, which is a great Drink in theſe Countries.</p>
                  <p>We that were behind after the reſt of the Fleet, two Evenings together near Sun-ſet, made another Saile; but night approaching, we loſt ſight of her, and the next day ſaw her at Anchor under <hi>Carthagene</hi> wall. We attempted to bring our Ships near her; but they diſcovering our intents, haled her aſhore, cutting their Cables; ſo that we being Ships of great burthen, had not depth of Water, beſides the danger of the Forts. We gave the Town a ſtrong Alarm, coming within ſhot, but they fired no Guns. So we left our chaſe, and with the advantage of a Weſterly wind (which is not uſuall here) we got up as high as <hi>Sancta Martha,</hi> and ſo ſtood over for <hi>Jamaica,</hi> leaving the other two Ships behind, where they chaſed another Veſſell into the ſhore, which ſuffered ſhipwrack there, laden with Tobacco, Hides, and Cocoes.</p>
                  <p>Severall Gentlemen from the Governour of <hi>Mevis</hi> have been here to view this Iſland of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Tranſplanting, who approve of the Ground very well, and are upon their Return with three of the States ſhips, to fetch the Governor, and their Families, and Eſtates.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37266:28"/>
            <head>A true Narrative of the late Succeſſe which it hath pleaſed God to give to ſome part of the Fleet of this Common-wealth, upon the Spaniſh Coast, againſt the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Weſt-India Fleet, in its return to <hi>Cadiz;</hi> being the ſubſtance of ſeverall Letters writ and ſent by the Generalls of the Fleet. <hi>Octob: 4. 1656.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="illustration">
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>battle between sailing ships</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Letter of Capt: <hi>Stayner,</hi> Commander of the Speaker Frigat, to Gen. <hi>Blake,</hi> and Gen. <hi>Montagu.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AFter my ſervice preſented to your Honors, theſe are to acquaint you, that upon the 8 inſtant at night it blew hard Weſterly, by means whereof we
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37266:29"/>with our Squadrons (onely the <hi>Providence</hi> was gone to water) weighed out of the Bay of <hi>Cadiz</hi> and plyed to Sea; in the evening we eſpied eight Sail ſome five or ſix leagues to the Weſtwards of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> we uſing the beſt means we could to meet with them the next day, which we did. It being little wind at N.E it was nine of the clock before we came up with them, but having a freſh gale in the night, all but we and the <hi>Bridgwater</hi> were to the Leeward, and could not come to us. But when we came to the Fleet, it proved to be the Spaniſh Fleet come from the Weſt-Indies, which were four of the King of <hi>Spains,</hi> three Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-men, and one Prize which they had taken by way of the Weſtern Iſlands being a Portugall, which were eight in all: We engaged the Fleet, but being within four leagues of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> could not ſtay for our ſhips, but we, the <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> and <hi>Plymouth,</hi> engaged them, and had a ſharp diſpute ſome of us; but the Admirall being the ſmalleſt ſhip, we ſleighted her, for we conceived there was ſome Pollicy uſed in the Flag, by which means their Admiral and the <hi>Portugall</hi> Prize got into <hi>Cadiz;</hi> the Vice-Admirall and one more we ſunk, and burnt two: We took one, the Captain of her, which we have on board, ſaith ſhe hath in her two Millions of ſilver; the Vice-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall had as much, I doe believe. The <hi>Plimouth</hi> chaſed another, who ran aſhore between S. <hi>Peters</hi> and <hi>Cape Degar,</hi> but it ſeems by the priſoners information ſhe had no ſilver in her; the ſhip we took was as good as all the Fleet beſides: the other that Captain <hi>Harman</hi> hath taken is very rich, but little ſilver in her. Both the Prize and our ſhip are ſorely wounded both in Maſt and Hull. The Commanders adviſe me not to take the ſilver out of her, I doe intend to take further
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37266:29"/>advice about it; there is no News, onely the Fleet I believe will follow us. The Gallies came out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the riches and diſability of our ſhips: we will come towards you except your Honours ſend further orders, for we are in no capacity to ſtay here. I ſhall leave two or three of the beſt ſayling ſhips off the Cape, and I and the reſt will come to <hi>Lisbone,</hi> where I hope to find your Honours. There is the <hi>Nova Spaniola</hi> Fleet at the <hi>Havana,</hi> but when they will come home is not known. This is all, onely there is loſſe of men in ſome ſhips, the number I know not. I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Honors most humble Servant,</hi> Ric: Stayner.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From on board the</hi> Speaker, <hi>in haste,</hi> 
                     <date>Sept. 9. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Letter of Gen. <hi>Blake,</hi> and Gen. <hi>Montagu</hi> to his Highneſſe the Lord Protector.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>May it pleaſe your Highneſſe.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEing out of water, and our Victualls almoſt ſpent, and having not heard from your Highneſſe, ſince the receipt of your commands by the Griffin, we found it requiſite to ſaile for this place, with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of the Fleet, as well to recruite our wants, as to be in a way of further order. Accordingly we arrived here on the 11 inſtant, and the 17 following in the night received the encloſed Account from the Commander of the Squadron left before <hi>Cadiz,</hi> which we humbly preſent to your Highneſſe; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping we ſhall be ſhortly able to informe your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe more particularly thereof, having ſent out what Frigots we could, as well to reinforce the Guard
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:37266:30"/>before <hi>Cadiz,</hi> as to ſecure the Prizes hither to us. In the mean time, the Providences that have come to our knowledge concurring to bring theſe ſhips into our hands, doe very much convince us it is of God in more than an ordinary manner; and we truſt it will by the ſame good hand be ſanctified unto us. We humbly take leave and remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Highnes very faithful and obedient Servants,</hi> Robert Blake. E: Mountagu.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From on board the</hi> Naſeby <hi>in the Bay of</hi> Wyers, <date>Sept. 19. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>An Account touching the great Deſtruction befallen the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in the Weſt-Indies.</head>
               <p>THE eldeſt ſon of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Badex</hi> (who was taken priſoner by our Fleet in the Spaniſh Vice-Admirall, as they came with their Silver from the Weſt-Indies) being examined, ſaith upon his Examination: That above five months ſince, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after his Father and Family departed out of <hi>Lima</hi> in <hi>Peru,</hi> there hapned a fearfull Earthquake and moſt miraculous Raine of fire from heaven in <hi>Peru,</hi> inſomnch that the whole City of <hi>Lima</hi> is ſwallowed up and deſtroyed, and alſo the City of <hi>Calao;</hi> in which places there periſhed above twelve thouſand Spaniards, and (to ſee the great diſtinguiſhing hand of God) not above one hundred Indians with them. In that City alſo, <hi>viz. Lima,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain</hi> hath loſt by the Earthquake, one hundred Millions of Silver ready wrought up. Moreover, the famous
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37266:30"/>Mines and Mountains of <hi>Potoſi</hi> (out of which they digged their Silver) are deſtroyed in a wonderfull manner, ſo that there is no more of Hills to be ſeen, but all plaine, nor is there any further poſſibility of having Gold or Silver in <hi>Peru.</hi> Some of the Spaniſh themſelves doe acknowledge, that this deſolation and deſtruction hath befaln the Spaniards for the Cruelties by them acted upon the poor Indians, they not ſparing even thoſe Indians among them who profeſſed the Roman Catholick Religion, inſomuch that the miſerable Creatures being beyond meaſure oppreſſed, and grieved with their ſufferings, cryed to Heaven for vengeance againſt them. Never was there a more terible viſible hand of God in judgment upon any people ſince the time of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah.</hi> Great is the Lord, marvellous are his doings, and to be had in reverence of all the Nations round about.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="narrative">
               <head>Here followeth the Narrative of the great Succeſſe given by God to a few of our Ships againſt the King of <hi>Spains</hi> Weſt-India Fleet.</head>
               <p>SEven Ships in the ſervice of the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (being four of the Kings own Fleet, and three Merchants) coming from the Weſt Indies, moſt of them richly laden with Gold Silver, Pearl, and other Commodities, <hi>viz.</hi> The Admirall, <hi>Don Marqueſſe Del porto</hi> Generall; The vice Admirall a Gallion, <hi>Don Franciſco De Eſquevel</hi> Commander; The Rere Admirall a Gallion, <hi>Don Franciſco Del Hayo</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a ſhip commanded by Captaine <hi>John Rhodrignes Caldron,</hi> a ſhip Commanded by Capt. <hi>John De la Tour,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:37266:31"/>another ſmall man of war, and a Veſſell of Advice from the <hi>Vice Roy</hi> of <hi>Mexico</hi> to <hi>Spain:</hi> They did in fifty eight days proceed ſo far as within a few leagues of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> without making Land or touching at any place during the voyage, having in their way betwixt the Weſtern Iſlands and <hi>Maſſagam</hi> in <hi>Affrick,</hi> ſeized upon a ſmall <hi>Portugall</hi> as Prize, by whom receiving a falſe information, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had beaten the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet from off their Coaſt, a month before; they ſayled with much confidence towards <hi>Cadiz</hi> as not expecting oppoſition.</p>
               <p>The greateſt part of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, were at this time gone to the Bay of <hi>Wyers</hi> in <hi>Portugall</hi> (where they arrived the eleventh of <hi>September</hi> laſt) to recruit their wants, and to be in a way of further Orders, the Generalls leaving behind them a Squadron of ſix or ſeven Ships (to have an eye upon <hi>Cadiz</hi>) under the command of Captain <hi>Stayner,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Speaker</hi> Frigot: which Squadron on the eight of <hi>September</hi> laſt, plying to Sea, being forced thither by a ſtrong Weſterly winde, did at the evening of the day Diſcover the ſaid Spaniſh Fleet, five or ſix Leagues to the Weſtward of <hi>Cadiz;</hi> And the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the night denying opportunity of preſent action, they endeavoured to fall in with them the next day, which accordingly they did about nine of the clock in the morning (they ſeeming to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards to be Fiſher-boats) But there being a freſh Gale that night, all but three of the Squadron were to the Leeward, and could not preſently come in, and finding it to be the Spaniſh Fleet come from the Indies, the <hi>Speaker,</hi> the <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> and the <hi>Plymouth</hi> Frigots (not thinking it adviſeable to ſtay for the reſt of the ſquadron, they being within 4 leagues of <hi>Cadiz</hi>)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37266:31"/>engaged with the Fleet, and a ſharp diſpute there was betwixt them: The Admirall being a ſmall ſhip, and it being conceived that the placing of the Flag upon her, might be in pollicy to divert them from attending the Ships of better value, they ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her, and ſuffered her (with the <hi>Portugall</hi> Prize) to go into <hi>Cadiz</hi> Bay, where (its ſaid) ſhe was run on ſhore and ſunk, being reported to have in her Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pieces of Eight: The Vice Admirall (being reported to have Six hundred thouſand pieces of Eight; beſides in Jewells and Plate, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Badex,</hi> to the value of five hundred thouſand pieces of Eight) having fought ſix hours, was taken by our Ships, and after ſet on fire by the Spaniards themſelves, and ſo burnt down, and ſnnk, in her were deſtroyed one hundred and ten men, the principalleſt of whom was the Marqueſſe of <hi>Badex,</hi> who with his wife and eldeſt daughter were burnt: The Rear Admirall was taken and remains in our poſſeſſion: The ſhip under the command of Captain <hi>John Rodrignes Caldron,</hi> which was ſaid to have in her Sugar, Tobacco and Plate, to the value of Six hundred thouſand pieces of Eight, was taken, and in the bringing off was by an accidentall fire burnt and ſunk: The ſhip under the command of <hi>De La Tour,</hi> twelve thouſand Weſt India Hides, and ſome quantities of Sugar, is taken and in our poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: The ſmall Man of War (having in her the like lading with the laſt mentioned) and the Advice Veſſell being of no force or lading, are ſaid to eſcape into <hi>Gibralter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The value of what is taken and poſſeſſed, is not juſtly known; but by the Calculation of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards there are taken and loſt about Nine Millions of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:37266:32"/>pieces of Eight: beſides the ſaid Ships and their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there are many priſoners taken, three hundred and fifty being found in the Rear Admiral, and about Ninety ſaved out of the Vice Admirall, amongſt whom there are the Eldeſt Son, a younger ſon, and two daughters of the ſaid Marqueſs of <hi>Badex,</hi> as alſo <hi>Don Diego De Villa Alva,</hi> the Governour of the <hi>Havana,</hi> and ſeverall others of quality, and Merchants.</p>
               <p>And all this was done without the loſſe of one Veſſell of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſo it pleaſed the wiſdome of God, to chuſe to effect ſo great a work, by a little force: As alſo by ſuffering the Enemy to be fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enſnared into a preſumptious confidence, by an Enemies information, on which they ſo relyed, that they neglected the haling of a Veſſell which came from St. <hi>Lucaz,</hi> and might have informed them of the truth.</p>
               <p>By this <hi>Narrative</hi> we ſee that the Lord whoſe right hand hath been heret ofore ſo glorious in power, for the help of his poor people in theſe Nations, in the time of their ſaddeſt dangers, when their Enemies at home expected to have ſatisfied their Luſts in their ruine, hath again appeared on their behalfe in this day of their need by blowing with his winds, and cauſing the Sea to cover their Enemies abroad, ſo that they have ſunk as Lead into the mighty waters, which gives abundant cauſe to ſay, <hi>who is like unto the Lord,</hi> for he hath triumphed Gloriouſly; and as the Eminency of this Mercy, in weakning the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy of Religion (the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> with whom this Commonwealth is engaged in a juſt and neceſſary war) and in encouraging and ſtrengthning the hands of his Servants, in a vigorous proſecution of that engagement, is much heightned by the freenes of <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:37266:32"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
